Hello, everyone. My name
is Dr. Ermin Tala, and
I'm a first-year internal
medicine resident at
Jacoby Einstein and a
recent NYTCOM graduate.
I want to welcome you
all to the first of
our four-part clinical
cardiology series.
I've been in your shoes,
and I'm extremely interested
and passionate about
cardiology, so I hope
that these lectures will
help you prepare for boards
and excel when you start
clinicals next year.
I'd also like to thank
Dr. Todd Cohen, who's
been a great role model,
mentor, and teacher
for allowing me to
lead these lectures.
The first of these
four lectures will
focus mainly on
normal physiology
and a fundamental
approach to the ECG.
As we go further into
the series, we'll
highlight more pathology
and take a macroscala
approach to the world
of clinical cardiology.
Most importantly, my goal
is to have you all think
critically and understand
these topics rather
than blunt memorization.
Trust me, if you take
this approach, it'll help
you succeed in the long
run, not just academically,
but also clinically.
So these are the session
objectives for this lecture.
The questions selected on
your upcoming exams, your
comps and pre-comps, will
reflect these objectives.
If you can answer these
questions in your own words,
you're probably in a good
spot. I've also attached in
the bottom right-hand corner
the corresponding first
aid page that can be used
for reference and for those
that may be accessing this
as supplemental material.
So now what is an ECG? An
electrocardiogram, an EKG
or ECG, is basically
just a visual or graphic
representation of the electrical
activity of the heart.
The ECG is comprised of 12
leads that are placed on
the chest or percordium and
all four leads. The ECG itself
is a snapshot of what's
going on electrically within
the heart. That's an important
thing to note as well
as it only provides us with
only 10 seconds of data.
It is an important tool that
can help us detect changes
within the electrical
activity of the heart that
kind of gives us some idea of
what's going on structurally
within the myocardium
during these cardiac cycles.
So the conduction system of
the heart basically dictates
this electrical pathway
that the heart follows. So
what we see in an ECG will
be a reflection of that,
making it important for us to
first understand the normal
path before we dive deeper
into specifics of the ECG.
So the conduction
pathway begins in the
right upper atrium
within the SA node,
travels down to the
atria, AV node, bundle
of his, right and
left bundle branches,
Purkinje fibers, and
then finally spreading
throughout the fibers
and the ventricles.
These structures do
have what's called
pacemaker rates,
basically rates,
heart rates that they
contract that individually.
The SA node is referred
to, it's called as the
pacemaker of the heart
because it is the quickest and
it dictates and pushes
the heart speed forward.
If you look at the SA
node, it's written that the
pacemaker rate is 60 to
100 beats per minute,
which kind of makes sense.
When we learned in medical
school that a normal heart
rate is between 60 to
100 beats per minute,
it's a reflection of the
SA node being the dominant
pacemaker of the heart.
The rest I've listed
there as well, they're not
particularly high yield
to know besides, like we
mentioned, the SA node,
because the SA node basically
will dictate what is not
Brady or Tachy arrhythmia.
So what is valuable for
you to understand is that
the SA node is the quickest
60 to 100 beats per
minute and then you can
also follow it up with the
AV node which is from 40
to 60 beats per minute.
Now pacemaking
speed is different
than conduction velocity.
Conduction velocity is
how fast the tissue can
depolarize. Now a good mnemonic
to remember from the fastest
to the slowest conduction
velocity is to use he
parked at Ventura Ave. This
was taken from first aid,
which is a super helpful
mnemonic. He parked
at Ventura Ave,
his Purkinje system
being the fastest,
followed by atria, followed
by ventricle, and
lastly, the AV node.
In a complete heart block
where there is complete
dissociation between the
atria and the ventricles,
the ventricles will be at
a rate unrelated to the
atria. It's an important
point to know for the future.
I did also add a little
tidbit at the end.
The SA node and AV node
receive their blood
supply from the right
coronary artery.
What would be the impact of an
inferior MI or heart attack?
Not something for you to
answer right now, just
something to keep in the
back of your mind as we
progress throughout the
series and for you to make
some integrations between
the lectures. So this is
another representation of
what we had spoken about,
the pacemaker speeds,
conduction velocities, etc.
This is basically formatted
in a tabular format,
which may make it easier
to learn the conduction
velocities, pacemaker
rates, and pathways.
So give this a look.
so now let's dive into the
parts of the EKG or ECG
within a rhythm strip you'll
find a number of what are
known as ECG complexes these
are individual representations
of one full heartbeat
during the cardiac cycle
try not to confuse the EKG
complex with the action
potentials that you taught,
which included phase 0, 1,
2, 3, 4, the EKG complex
is not an action potential.
As we take a more macro view
of the heart's electricity,
it's important to
also keep in mind the
principles related to the
cardiac muscle and nodal action
potentials at the cellular
level. You can refer to
these lectures about action
potential physiology.
If you're good at the
alphabet, you should be
good at the next part.
To label on the EKG
complex, we utilize the
letters P, Q, R, S, and T.
Over the following few
slides, we'll discuss
what each of these
inflections represents.
On the slide, you'll
also find segments and
intervals. These both
represent a period between two
events, not a specific
inflection point. A segment
is defined as a line,
usually isoelectric,
connecting two waves without
including either one.
The most clinically
significant of these
segments is the ST segment,
which signifies the
presence of an ST
elevation myocardial
infarction, aka a STEMI,
as we see on the right.
An interval is defined
as a portion of the EKG
that includes a segment
and one or more wave.
An example here, PR
interval, QT interval.
A clinically relevant
interval is that QT
interval that can
become prolonged when
a patient is given
some particular drugs.
A prolonged QT interval
can push a patient into
what's known as the SARS
-Dipoint, a potentially fatal
arrhythmia that can
degenerate to ventricular
tachycardia and furthermore
ventricular fibrillation.
so now we have what's
called the p wave so the
pacemaker cells in the
sa node also known as the
sinoatrial node initially
begins depolarizing
the atria this is the p
wave the p wave is not
the contraction of the
atria just the preceding
depolarization now reminder
that a rhythm strip
shows electrical
conductance, not contraction.
That being said, as the
P-wave occurs, the atria
is coordinating its squeeze
of the blood into the
ventricles past the mitral
and tricuspid valves.
The left atrium is further
than the right atrium in
terms of anatomical
positioning relative to the SA
node. Given the position
of the SA node, there's a
slight delay in the
contraction of the left atrium.
Note that this is both
the atria contracting when
referring to the P wave. So
if one atria is larger than
the other, the P wave may
appear as a double hump.
An intra-atrial delay is
present, meaning that one
atria contracts before another.
This would yield a double
hump as well. If the
atria hypertrophied, the P
wave amplitude will be much
more prominent in voltage.
Now saying this in simple
terms, basically the P
wave as we see here is
a summation of atrial
depolarization and contraction
of the atrial. It's a
summation meaning that it
takes into account both left
atrial and right atrial
depolarization. When we get
the summation of the two,
that's how we get a nice
P wave hump, as we see
here. Now, there are times
where you can see a
double hump, which is also
called P mitrale, but that's
for a later discussion.
Now, let's talk about
the PR interval. So,
the PR interval is the
time that takes from
the start of the
atrial depolarization
to the start of
ventricular depolarization.
Basically, the PR interval
represents conduction
from the SA to the AV
node. This occurs by
travel through the atrial
ventricular AV node.
If there's some sort of
conduction issue at the AV
node, you would see this
as a prolonged PR interval.
Now, a normal PR interval is
from 120 to 200 milliseconds.
It's important to know
these normal interval
durations when it comes
to interpreting EKGs.
A prolonged PR interval
can become clinically
significant in what is known
as an AV block, heart block.
We'll discuss AV blocks
in a later lecture, but
there are different types
of AV blocks that range from
first to third degree
which can alter management.
Next we have the QRS
complex. So the QRS complex
represents the polarization
of the ventricles.
The Q is the first part
of the downstroke seen
right here followed by the
R which is the upstroke
and lastly, the S, the
second down stroke. This
complex is easily identifiable
due to its increased
amplitude relative to
the P and the T waves.
The QRS complex's length
is used to determine any
electrical conductance issues,
whether it be blockages
at the left bundle, right
bundle, or the fascicles.
Other reasons why QRS may be
prolonged include hyperkalemia,
tricyclic antidepressants,
sodium channel blocking agents,
Wolf-Parkinson-White syndrome,
etc.
QRS amplitude height
may be altered
in a few pathologic conditions.
It's increased in left
ventricular hypertrophy,
right ventricular hypertrophy,
also in more frail
patients. It is lower or
decreased in amplitude in
obese patients and in the
setting of pericarditis.
A little fun fact, the QRS
complex is also known as
a QR interval, as it meets
the criteria to be an
interval. A QRS interval of
less than 100 is considered
normal, but for a second
year medical student level,
120 is considered normal.
Clinicians use a QRS
interval of 110 to
120, sometimes 100
to 120, to signify
ventricular conduction
defects and delays.
Next we have the ST
segment. So the ST segment
represents the mechanical
contraction of the ventricles.
As stated a few slides
ago, this is clinically
relevant in the case of
a STEMI, where the ST
segment rises in anatomically
contiguous leads.
We'll discuss which
leads are associated with
distinct areas of the
heart and specific
coronary arteries in the
following the lectures.
But this just goes to
show SC segment is a
very important segment to
be aware of, especially
in the context of
MIs or heart attacks.
Next is the T-wave,
which represents
ventricular repolarization.
Whenever I hear T
-wave, I think potassium
lives under the T-wave.
So in hyperkalemia,
where there's an
increase in K, there's
an increase in the
amplitude of a T-wave.
In hypokalemia, the T-wave
will flatten and may even
cause a predominant U
-wave, which looks like an
inverted T-wave and is something
we'll discuss later on.
Lastly, we have the QT
interval, which describes the
time from ventricular
depolarization to ventricular
repolarization. A prolonged
QT interval increases the risk
of ventricular arrhythmias,
mainly torsades de point.
There is a condition also
known as congenital long QT
syndrome, and the most
common form is autosomal
dominant. For this reason, we
screened those with a family
history of sudden cardiac
death for these conditions.
A good rule of thumb
is that a normal QT
interval is less than
half of the R to R ratio.
We'll get into
more specifics on
normal durations
in later lectures.
i chose to also include a
list of drugs and a mnemonic
to remember the drugs
that may cause a long qt
it goes by anti abcdef you
may have also seen this
in your first aid book but
just something to gloss
over and to keep in mind
especially for exams and
definitely for clinical
practice when you're dealing
with patients who may need
some of these medications
and have or are at risk of
a prolonged QT interval.
So putting this all
together, you can see how the
information given to us on
an ECG can be reflective
of what is going on
structurally in the heart.
The electrical pathway through
the heart is as follows.
The pacemaker cells of
the SA node, located
between the opening
of the superior necava
and the upper wall
of the right atrium,
depolarize and induce
contraction of the atria.
The conductance then
goes to the AV node
located on the floor of
the right atrium, where
it travels through the
right and left bundle
branches. On the left
bundle branch, you'll
find an anterior and
posterior fascicle.
Lastly,
the Purkinje fibers
finish the conduction
system before exciting
the heart muscle. As a
review, if there is any
block in any of these
steps, you'll find
either a prolonged PR
interval or QRS complex
or no conduction. Here's
a GIF that any visual
learner can use and to
associate the cardiac
cycle with the ECG complex.
It's a bit quick, so feel
free to slow down the
video and review this
alongside your previous notes.
So here's a question
that you can answer.
I recommend pausing
the video now.
All right, so time is up.
So which of the
following represents
ventricular repolarization?
A, QRS complex, B, P
-wave, or C, T-wave.
Now, if you don't have
the answer yet, I suggest
again pausing it because
here comes the answer.
Now, the main distractor
in this question is the QRS
complex, as it represents
ventricular depolarization.
But it's the T-wave,
choice C, that represents
ventricular repolarization.
And as we know from
before, the P wave represents
atrial depolarization.
Okay, same setup as before.
I'd recommend pausing
the video for about five
seconds and returning when
you have an answer in mind.
All right.
So here we have a 29-year
-old male with depression
presents to your office
with a family history
of sudden death in his
uncle and grandfather.
He has tried multiple SSRIs
and SNRIs to no success.
He's interested in
starting imipramine.
On EKG, you'll be
most worried about
the A, PR interval,
or B, QT interval.
So imipramine, which
is important to
know in the context
of this question,
is a tricyclic
antidepressant, a TCA.
It's only relatively used for
refractory cases of depression.
TCAs can cause an
increase in QT intervals.
With this patient's
family history, which
looks relatively
concerning for congenital
long QT syndrome, we
should probably get
an EKG to examine this
current QT interval.
Okay, so now placement
of ECG leads. This is
particularly important.
Why? Because when you begin
your clinical rotations,
especially as a med
student, you'll likely be
asked to do two things.
grab an EKG, and draw blood.
So, during your clinical
rotations, you're
probably going to be
the one who's going to
grab the EKG machine
and place the electrodes
on the patient's
chest and extremities.
So, now it's important to
go over the placement of
these electrodes, which you
can see on the screen here.
So, there are two
families of electrodes.
The first, shown on
the left, are referred
to as limb leads. Named
for pretty obvious
reasons, they're
placed on the limbs.
There's a mnemonic that
Dr. Cohen taught me to
help put the limb leads
in the correct spot.
I've circled it as well
on the bottom right hand
corner. So the mnemonic
goes green and white on the
right Christmas tree below
the knees. This refers to
green, the right leg, and
white, the right arm being
on the right side of the
body, while the green right
leg and red left leg
being the two lower limbs.
This will give you enough
information to impress your
attending. So now the cordial
leads are named as such
because they are in front
of the chest, precordial.
You can start by placing
V1 on the right side of
the sternal border at the
fourth intercostal space.
V2 is on the opposite left
side of the sternum as
well at the fourth intercostal
space. Then you can
place V4 at the fifth
intercostal space mid-clavicular
line, round it back to V3,
which is between V2 and
V4, and then V5 is on the
anterior axillary line next
to V4 and V6 next to V5
on the mid-axillary line.
The location of the
leads, basically the way
they're positioned, will
give different positive
or negative voltage
inflections on the EKG,
so it's important to have
them placed correctly
and in their anatomical
and correct positions.
We'll discuss this further once
we look at EKGs
in a few slides.
Many patients have an
understanding that an ECG
is a way of looking
at the health of the
heart. However, as a
medical student, you'll now
identify minor or major
cardiac abnormalities.
This may change your medical
management or may have
you consult cardiology
if you're unsure about a
unique circumstance.
By the end of this four
lecture series, you'll be
able to identify common
arrhythmias, acute coronary
syndromes, and be able to
tell a patient this is a
normal healthy EKG. You
may see an ECG presented
to you in two different
ways, as a 12-lead on
a piece of paper or
a rhythm strip on a
strip of paper. A 12-lead
gives you information on
all parts of the heart,
while a rhythm strip
gives you continuous
information on one aspect
or view of the heart.
If you're handed a paper
and see 12 leads, it's
a 12-lead or complete
view of the heart. If
you're handed one single
piece of paper and only
see a single lead, that's
called a rhythm strip.
You will, for the most
part, see 12 leads,
but while on rotations,
especially on
telemetry or during
your code, you'll likely
be given a rhythm
strip to interpret.
The more rhythm strips you
get of different leads,
the more data you have that
you can correlate clinically
with your patient. And if
you were to take rhythm
strips of all 12 leads, you
would get a 12-lead EKG.
If you look at the bottom
of an ECG, you will likely
see only one lead. In this
example, we see lead 2.
This is an example of
a rhythm strip that is
included as a preset
option on the EKG machine
and gives you a longer
duration of view.
The complete 10 seconds
versus the leads above
that are about 2.5
seconds in duration each.
Now that we're oriented
to the leads as they are
placed on the patient and
through a clinical lens,
it is time to get a fresh
look at a 12-lead ECG.
It is called a 12-lead
because there are 12
unique views that give
us unique information.
So first we have box
in yellow on the left
of an EKG. you'll identify
leads 1, 2, 3, AVR,
AVL, and AVF. It
may be confusing to
understand what these
mean as they aren't leads
that we directly put
on the patient's body.
We will be discussing
how they're
calculated in the
next objective.
On the right, boxed in
red, you'll find the
electrical activity identified
through the pecordial
leads, V1 to V6, like
we mentioned before.
At the bottom, as
mentioned a few slides
ago also, you'll
see a rhythm strip.
Commonly, like we
mentioned, you'll
see lead 2 as the rhythm strip.
Occasionally, the leads
will not be labeled,
so you will need to have
a system to remember
where the leads lie
on the 12-lead ECG.
I usually first start with
1, 2, 3 down the column,
then we run into AVR, AVL,
AVF, which can be remembered
as RALF, R-A-L-F. The last
two columns are V1 to V6.
So in conclusion, the
limbs and augmented leads
are found on the left
side, while the chest
or precordial leads
are found on the right.
Now I'm going to
introduce a concept
known as direction of
electrical voltage.
As stated before, the
location of the leads
determines both amplitude
and whether or not the
voltage goes up, positive,
or down, negative.
The terminology to refer to a
more upward QRS is positive.
Here, the R is further
from baseline than the S.
In a more negative
inflection, the R is
smaller than the S.
This is termed negative.
While the R and S are the same
lengths away from the baseline,
this is referred
to as equiphasic.
An important point now.
So voltage is positive when
depolarization occurs
towards the lead.
Voltage is negative
when depolarization
occurs away from the lead.
Let me repeat that
because understanding
that is vital to
the next objective.
Voltage is positive when
depolarization occurs
toward the lead.
Voltage is negative when
depolarization occurs
away from the lead.
The precordial leads show
how location affects the
voltage in what is referred
to as R-wave progression.
As you move further
down from the middle
of the chest, you
will notice that the R
becomes more positive
from V1 to V2 to V3.
In fact, it is one good
indicator of heart health
if you have a good R-wave
progression. You're usually
obtaining an equiphasic,
also known as biphasic,
QRS complex once you get
between V3 and V4. So
now, as you did prior,
pause your screen
for about five
seconds, answer the
question, and then
return when you're ready.
All right.
So this question
states, which of the
following cannot be
identified by an ECG?
A, STEMI, B, primary
biliary coangitis, or
C, arrhythmia such as
atrial fibrillation.
So when a person
arrives to the ER or
complains of chest
pain, discomfort, or
pressure, you're
thinking EKG, STAT.
We need to rule out some
sort of acute coronary
syndrome, be it STEMI and
STEMI or unstable angina.
Arrhythmias, also
detected by an EKG, may
present with palpitations,
heart skipping a
beat, or feeling that
there are additional
beats. You can also
present with chest pain,
shortness of breath,
syncope, or presyncope
in the form of dizziness.
Only of these options
of this question,
only primary biliary
cholangitis, which is
an inflammatory bowel
disease of the biliary
tree, is not identified
through an EKG.
so same routine as before
pause the video look over
the question and see what
you can come up as an
answer but let's just dive
right into it so we have an
84 year old female with
a past medical history of
uncontrolled hypertension
and diabetes presents with
crushing chest pain radiating
down the arm for the
past 40 minutes ems has
provided her with nitroglycerin
aspirin oxygen, and
morphine on route that has
mildly assisted the patient.
The EKG is not attached
on arrival and your
attending asks you to place a
white lead on the patient.
You place it on the right
arm. Will your attending
be disappointed in you?
I hope you answered
similarly to the way
I did. No, my attending
would be proud.
As we learned before from
our mnemonic, green and white
on the right christmas tree
below the knees we know
that the white lead would
end up on the right arm so
now this will give
you enough information
especially using this
mnemonic to impress
your attendings and
hopefully never get
the limb lead electrode
placements wrong
And option two is
also an answer.
Okay, so now we're
going to talk about the
orientation of the heart.
So the orientation of the
atrium ventricles doesn't
mimic their names.
In fact, the name of the
atrium ventricles with
right and left denotes
their embryologic origin.
Unfortunately, this makes
learning orientation
as a medical student
a bit annoying.
The angle of the heart,
meaning the direction
from the base to
the apex, is rotated
left and retroverted,
a.k.a. tilted back.
The most anterior
chamber in the chest
is the right
ventricle, and the most
posterior chamber
is the left atrium.
Keep this in mind as the
pathway of the electrical
conductance is relayed
in the same direction.
now we'll introduce the idea
of a vector which is the
basis for all leads but
right now we'll focus on how
they construct the limb
leads i'll preface this with
the fact that this is
probably the most conceptually
difficult concept in these
four lectures sorry in
advance for bringing you
back to the introduction of
physics but it's pretty
important so in physics a
vector basically is a quantity
that holds both magnitude
and direction. You can
think of speed and velocity.
Speed just telling
you how fast you're
going versus velocity
telling you how fast
you're going and in
which direction. In that
case, velocity being
a vector quantity.
For our purposes,
everything on an EKG
is a vector because it
highlights both the
amplitude, the amount, and
voltage direction. And
the next slide will be
introduced to what's known
as Eindhoven's triangle.
Eindhoven's triangle
is a series of vectors
that will help you
visualize and understand
what 1, 2, 3, AVR, AVL, and AVF
actually look like from
a vector perspective.
So now look at the picture
on the left, Eindhoven's
triangle. Let's orient
ourselves to what it
represents. This is an
anterior view of the chest. The
triangle's three points
are the right arm lead, the
left arm lead, and the
left lower limb lead. The
heart is situated on the
left side of the chest,
so all vector calculations,
including lower leads,
utilize the left lower
limb for a more accurate
vector. The easiest
to understand is lead
1, which is the potential
between the right
arm and the left arm.
This is a straight line
across and is the
triangle's base at the top.
Lead 2 is the potential
between the right arm and
the lower limb. Lead 3 is
the potential between the
left arm and the lower limb.
The electrical potential
of the heart moves to the
left and downward because
that's how the normal
conduction system of the
heart functions like we
reviewed before it starts at
the sa node and then moves
down towards the ventricles
the left ventricle itself
is thicker and larger
than the right which is why
the potential moves more
so towards the right rather
than the left so basically
everything all moves
towards the left ventricle
mnemonic to remember
this is seen on the slide
mnemonic hasn't helped me
much but maybe it'll help you
you can count the number
of l's something we are
very accustomed to in medical
school to identify which
leads it differentiates
so if it helps use it now
leads avr avl and avf
stand for augmented
vector right
augmented vector left
augmented vector
foot respectfully
The naming can help you
remember where they're
pointing. For example,
augmented vector right points to
the right arm. To complete
Eindhoven's triangle, you
add a perpendicular line
to the middle 1, 2, and 3.
AVR is perpendicular to
lead 3, AVL is perpendicular
to lead 2, and AVF
is perpendicular to
lead 1. A mnemonic to
remember this is RALF321.
So you may be asking
yourself, why is Ion
-Telphine's triangle
clinically relevant, and
why do we waste so
much time and energy
discussing something so
conceptually difficult?
Now, throughout the past
few slides, we've discussed
the orientation of the
heart. That is, the heart
is angled down and to the
left. This means that the
voltage should also be
angled down and to the left.
Ion-Telphine's triangle
can be reconstructed into
zones that can tell us
where the angle of the
heart's electoral activity
is going. This is also
clinically significant in
the aspect of reading ECGs.
It gives rise to what
is known as axis.
So the axis is
defined as the major
direction of the heart's
electrical activity.
We utilize zero
degrees as lead one.
And any diversion
counterclockwise would
have a negative
angle away from zero.
and clockwise would be a
positive inflection from zero.
The normal axis of
the heart ranges from
between negative
30 and positive 60.
Going back to our understanding
of ECG physiology,
if a positive voltage
refers to direction
towards, we can use a
positive inflection in the
QRS complex to determine
whether or not we
have an axis going in
a particular direction.
There are a few ways
to determine the
axis, but we'll discuss
it physiologically.
Then, in the following
lecture, you'll learn a
quicker way to help you on
your clinical rotations.
So the two major
leads that we use when
determining axes are
leads 1 and leads AVF.
We use these two leads because
they're perpendicular
to each other.
If the QRS complexes are
positive in both lead 1 and
AVF, then we know we're
between 0 and 90 degrees.
If either of these is
negative, we know that
there's a possibility of
some sort of deflection
away from the normal
axis. It could be a
left axis deviation or
a right axis deviation.
These deflections could even be
extreme or far
right or far left.
Here we can see both
lead 1 and lead AVF are
upright or positive in
their QRS complexes.
So if we were to
draw this out, as
we mentioned, lead
1 and lead AVF.
The QRS complex
in AVF is upright,
as we see also in
lead 1, so it means
that the ECG shows
a non-deviated
normal axis between
0 and 90 degrees. So
now time for a question.
Feel free to pause
the video and come
back when you're ready.
So, in this question,
it asks, which
of the following are
precordial leads?
A, lead 1, B, lead AVF, C, lead
V4, or D, none of the above?
Now, as you probably have
deduced, the answer is
C, V4. Lead 1 and AVF are
considered limb leads,
while before it's considered
a precordial lead.
And now we have a 74-year
-old male presents the
ER complaining of severe
substernal chest pain. You
quickly triage and see
that this patient may be
presenting with a STEMI,
so you order a STAT EKG.
Your attending asks you
to identify the axis.
Which pair of leads is most
suitable for this purpose?
Is it A, lead AVF
and 2, or B, AVF
and AVR, or C,
lead one and AVF.
Now, spoiler alert,
as you mentioned
before, your best options
are, again, always
to compare lead one
to lead AVF, given
that they are perpendicular
to each other.
We'll talk about this
more as we continue in our
lecture series, but good
tidbit to know for now.
So this is just a summary slide
with some extra information.
This is definitely pretty
high yield to know and I
would definitely take some
time to look over this
definitely at your
own pace and make
sure you have a good
understanding of
the material that
we've covered so far.
I've also included some
tips and tad bits about how
I would approach the lecture.
maybe it'll be useful
so feel free
to look over it
alright
and as always feel free
to reach out for questions
to myself and the rest of
the Cohen research team
and again like every
skill more exposure means
better skill development
and build up Dr. Cohen has
his Monday lunch and learn
ECG lecture series that's
sent out every week by
the Cohen research team.
And feel free to
leave some feedback
on the lecture.
Best of luck to you
guys and see you in
the next lecture.